Register of the Georgiĭ Titovich Kii͡ashchenko papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Georgiĭ Titovich Kii͡ashchenko papers
circa 1910-1948
2001C32
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 2 envelopes, 3 microfilm reels (0.8 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, military documents, printed matter, and photographs relating to Russia in World War I and to Russian émigré affairs.
Kii͡ashchenko, Georgiĭ Titovich.
Location of Originals
In part, originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual or digital material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Biographical Note
General Georgiĭ Titovich Kii͡ashchenko was born in the town of Starodub in 1872. He was educated at the Chuguev Military School, and his military career culminated with the rank of major general and the title of director of military transport in the Far East in 1919. He was a participant in the Russian army's 1915 Lodz operation, about which he left notes for a lecture. In San Francisco in the 1920s and 1930s, Kii͡ashchenko became an active participant in Russian Orthodox Church politics and the émigré monarchist movement.
Most of his views on these subjects were expressed in the pages of Nashe slovo and Viera i pravda, and a number of other pamphlets, periodicals and leaflets, which he edited and published. He supported the Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia, as well as the Grand Duke Vladimir Kirillovich's claim to the Russian throne. Kii͡ashchenko died in San Francisco on 19 January 1940.
Scope and Content of Collection
Speeches and writings, correspondence, military documents, printed matter, and photographs relating to Russia in World War I and to Russian émigré affairs.
Scope and Content of Microfilm Portion of Collection
SPEECHES AND WRITINGS contains the periodicals Nashe slovo and Viera i pravda, which Kii͡ashchenko edited and published in San Francisco. There is also a large amount of related material, including appeals by various organizations, in the SUBJECT FILE. Also of interest are the letters and notices in CORRESPONDENCE from the Ob"edinenie Chuguevskago voennago uchilishcha, of which Kii͡ashchenko was a member.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russians--United States.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Journalists.
- Biographical File, 1929-1939
  Scope and Contents note
  Clipping, commendation, and programs, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Clippings mentioning Kiiashchenko (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 1
  - Commendation (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 2
  - Programs of public events featuring Kiiashchenko (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 3
- Correspondence, 1928-1939 and undated
  Letters and attachments, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General, 1929-1939 and undated (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 4
  - Unidentified, 1934 and undated (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 5
  - Apollinarii, Bishop, 1928 (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 6
  - Feofil, Metropolitan, 1934-1936 (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 7
  - Ob"edinenie Chuguevskago voennago uchilishcha, 1936-1938 and undated (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 8
    Includes attachments.
  - Tolstov, Sergei, 1937-1938 (Reel 1)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 9
- Speeches and Writings, 1927-1940
  Notes, articles and fragments of articles, speeches, and letters to the editor, arranged chronologically by title. See also Subject File for leaflets and brochures by other authors issued by Kii͡ashchenko, including articles and editorials by him.
  - General
    - General, 1935-1938 and undated (Reel 1)
      Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 10
      Includes notebooks with holograph drafts of articles and letters to the editor, notes, fragments of works, appeals, flyers and leaflets composed by Kiiashchenko, 1938 and undated.
    - Letters to the editor, 1927-1934 and undated (Reel 1)
      Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 11
    - Periodicals edited, issued, and primarily authored by Kiiashchenko, 1928-1939 and undated
      - Mirianin, 1928 and undated (Reel 1)
        Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 12
      - Viera i pravda
        General note
        Bound volumes lack those issues placed at head of series.
        - #5, 11, 15, 16, 41, 51, 1930-1934 (Reel 1)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 13
        - #1-22, 1930-1931 (Reel 1)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 14
        - #23-39, 1931-1933 (Reel 1)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 1: 15
        - #40-58, 1933-1936 (Reel 2)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 1
      - Listki v chest' Bratstva Sv. Rusi imeni Sv. Kniazia Vladimira, fragment, 1934 February and undated (Reel 2)
        Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 2
      - Letuchka "Viesti", #1-9, 1935 May 1 - September 15 (Reel 2)
        Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 3
      - Nasha gazeta
        - Distribution records (Reel 2)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 4
        - Printed copies, #21-37 (incomplete), 1936 June 17 - 1937 December 28 (Reel 2)
          Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 5
      - Nashe slovo, #41-54 (fragment, incomplete), 1938 June 1 - 1939 October 26 and undated (Reel 2)
        Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 6
  - "Ekaterinburgskoe zlodieianie prodolzhaetsia," typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 7
  - "Imperator Nikolai II i Gosudarstvennaia Duma," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 8
  - "K poznaniiu istokov Rossiiskoi razrukhi," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 9
  - "Kak eto nachalos'," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 10
  - "Kliuch k edinstvu russkago razsieianiia," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 11
  - "Kornilovskoe vozstanie," holograph, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 12
  - "Kto zhe on poslie 10-12 lietnei davnosti?," typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 13
  - "Lodz'," speech before an audience at the Russian Club, San Francisco, holograph, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 14
    Includes advertisements.
  - "Mirovaia missiia Rossii," speech before an audience at the Russian Club, San Francisco, holograph, typescript, and printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 15
  - "Nashi dielishki," typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 16
  - "Natsional'naia revoliutsiia," typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 2: 17
  - "O griadushchikh sud'bakh Rossii," holograph and typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 18
  - "O tsarstvie mira na zemlie," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 19
  - "Pamiati Arkhiepiskopa Apollinariia," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 20
  - "Pia Desideria," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 21
  - "Pis'ma k russkoi molodezhi," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 22
  - "Pochemu sniaty preshcheniia i vozstanovlena sovmiestnaia molitva," holograph, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 23
  - "Poiezdka v Sakramento," holograph, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 24
  - "Politicheskoe znachenie osvobozhdeniia krest'ian," holograph, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 25
  - "Pora okonchit' spory," Russkaia mysl', printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 26
  - "Poslie konfuza," typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 27
    Includes associated correspondence.
  - "Samoopredielenie russkikh emigrantov," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 28
  - "Smysl i sposoby bor'by s Internatsionalom," typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 29
  - "Sprav.[edlivost'?] i moral'," typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 30
  - "Stoianie za pravdu," typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 31
  - "Tserkovnaia parodoksal'nost'," printed copy, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 32
  - Untitled work on émigré politics, holograph, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 33
  - Untitled work on Russian Orthodox Church affairs abroad, typescript, undated (Reel 2)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 2: 34
  - "Vuslushai i druguiu storonu," typescript, undated (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 1
  - "Zamietki k temie 'General Kornilov'," holograph, undated (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 2
  - "Zhutkii vopros: Za chto?," typescript, undated (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 3
  - "Besiedy k poznaniiu Rossii: Soznanie russkimi liud'mi ikh gosudarstvennoi idei," holograph, 1931 (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 4
  - "S nami Bog," printed copy, 1931 January (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 5
  - "O prichinakh 'Rokovoi oshibki'," Viera i pravda, printed copy, 1931 July 29 (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 6
  - "Besieda o dushevnykh zabolievaniiakh obshchestva," printed copy, 1935 October (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 7
  - "Diela da sluchai," typescript, [1938] (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 8
  - Komu nuzhna byla gibel' Rossii, printed copy, 1939 (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 9
  - "Khristianskii mistitsizm," typescript, 1940 January 8 (Reel 3)
    Russian Museum of Culture Box/Folder 3: 10
- Subject File, 1922-1948
  Includes clippings, leaflets and brochures by other authors issued by Kii͡ashchenko, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Monarchy--Russia (Reel 3)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 3: 11
    Includes appeals, brochures, bulletins, and other materials relating to the émigré monarchist movement.
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' (Reel 3)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 3: 12
    Primarily concerns conflicts within the Russian Orthodox Church abroad in the 1920s and 1930s.
  - Miscellany (Reel 3)
    Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 3: 13
    Appeals, clippings, leaflets, brochures and writings on a variety of subjects, primarily of a religious or political nature.
- Photographs, undated (Reel 3)
  Museum of Russian Culture Box/Folder 3: 14
  One print of Admiral A. V. Kolchak and one of an unidentified individual, possibly Kii͡ashchenko's son.
- Incremental Materials (Box 1, Envelope A-B)
  Original materials added to microfilm collection from the Museum of Russian Culture.